WWW.MY-SUBS.CO
Welcome backstage
to Auckland's Civic Theatre.
We are live
with the two-hour season final
of Survivor New Zealand
and here they are,
this season's players.
Remember Lou, whose shock
departure from Mogoton
caused a shakeup
that changed everything.
Mikey here was de-throned,
the game was turned on its head
and it's not over yet.
Later, I'll read the votes,
announced the winner and open up
the stage for a chat.
Then, there's the GEM
People's Choice Award
and all in front
of this epic crowd
here at The Civic.
So, here's where we're at.
Just three left in the game.
Tom, who fought his way
to the top,
amazing in challenges,
Avi the best social player
of the season,
and Barb
who made the biggest moves.
Now, we head into day 39
still uncertain
who will take the title
of sole survivor
and the one hundred
thousand dollars
that goes with it.
Here it is, the season final
of Survivor New Zealand.
Previously,
on Survivor New Zealand.
Sixteen castaways
embarked on the adventure
of a life-time.
Welcome to Nicaragua,
and New Zealand's
first ever Survivor.
Wahoo.
They split into two tribes,
Mogoton and Hermosa.
This is wicked!
Set up camp in the jungle.
Bring it all in here
then we'll see
what we've got and figure out
what we're gonna build, aye?
- Go team.
- Built alliances.
As long as we know
we're a strong three.
- Yeah.
And quickly turned on those
they saw as the toughest.
First person
voted out of Hermosa tribe,
Dee.
Or the weakest.
Hannah, the tribe has spoken.
I wanna be the good person
that does the decent thing,
and then I want to be
a Survivor.
So you almost can't play
the two at the same time.
But just when they thought
they had the game sussed,
they were met with a twist,
Redemption Island.
Go Hannah!
Come on!
Redemption Island
offers an opportunity
for you to duel your way
back into this competition.
Hannah is through the door
and lives to fight another day.
Dee, you are the first person
eliminated
from Survivor New Zealand.
At Mogoton, the tribe
turned on their
self-appointed leader.
Tony, the tribe has spoken.
While at Hermosa,
it was generation
against generation.
We've got five young ones.
- Yes, I am concerned.
- The old people
were gonna target you two,
I heard.
I think Nate's a massive threat.
I don't know what Barb
would do though.
She's the kind of person that
would just get tagged along,
and then end up at the end
and everyone would be like,
"How the hell did she get there?
As Hermosa proved stronger
in immunity challenges.
- Louisa is gone.
- Hey bro.
Shay campaigned
to take out arch-rival Tom.
I want Tom out.
I know he's after me.
I think we should carry Tom
a little bit.
But with Avi's help...
Tom survived.
Third person
voted out of Mogoton...
At Izzy's expense.
It was a close call tonight.
I don't feel safe.
The medical evacuation
of Louisa stunned Mogoton.
- Love you girl.
- She's a firecracker.
She's gonna be missed.
It's time to drop your buffs,
we're redrawing for new tribes.
And led to a tribal re-shuffle.
- Ye.
- Yeah Lee!
Bringing new hope
to Nate and Barb.
Barb and I've been dead
in the water for days.
Now the whole game's
been turned on its head.
Go!
A new stronger Mogoton emerged.
Mogoton wins immunity!
And gave Tom a fresh start.
- Gallo!
- Pinto!
It's kinda like a bachelor party
- without the alcohol.
- Survivor Enchilada!
Except one of them has brought
their angry missus.
The new-look Hermosa
gave Nate and Barb the chance
to eliminate
one of their young foes.
- She's got to go.
- Georgia.
While the Mogoton brotherhood...
- Mogoton, struggling.
- Good, good, good.
Threw a crucial
immunity challenge.
- Hey!
- Hermosa win immunity!
To move against their nemesis.
First person voted out
of the new-look Mogoton tribe,
Shay.
Georgia, crumbling!
But Shay played her way back in.
Shay is back in this game!
Right in time
for a massive shake-up.
Everyone, drop your buffs.
Congratulations guys,
you've made it to the merge.
You are now the Casar tribe,
which means "to marry"
in Spanish.
- But the honey-moon...
- We thank you for this merge.
Was short-lived,
as two alliances
grappled for supremacy.
With Tom trying
to get Avi to change sides.
You know, with the five on our
side, none of us will flip.
And Shannon
playing a double game.
I am jumping
between both camps so fast.
I've got lies
going all over the place.
- I'm sorry.
- Lee.
A surprise double elimination.
- Michael.
- What the hell?
Sent two
of the strongest players
to Redemption Island.
Both just wondering
how we went from hero
to zero just now really.
Destroying the boys' alliance.
But a sleeping giant woke.
And made her move.
I can start manipulating people.
And all of a sudden
she's like a mafia queen.
We'll do Sala first.
Busting
her alliance from within.
Third person voted out
of Casar is...
And blindsiding
one of its kingpins.
Sala.
Barb you are good.
I know
everyone's underestimated me.
I'm a hundred-percent
I'm the next to go.
I do trust you and Barb, still.
While Avi scrambled
to avoid elimination.
Jak, the tribe has spoken.
Jak bared more than his soul.
Tom was still a target.
We really need
to send Tom to Redemption.
Again, Tom wins immunity!
But as he clung
onto the immunity necklace,
Shannon's days were numbered.
The tribe has spoken.
Then, loyalties were tested.
You have to vote Shay as well.
I promised her I'd never write
her name down.
As the tribe went after Shay.
I really wish I could have
saved you this time.
Barb faced a tough choice
between friend and alliance.
I'm a bit emotional today.
- Thank you very much.
- Nate.
Yes I'm down on one knee,
but I've got a fighting chance
haven't I?
Over seventeen days.
Michael is sweet
and stays alive in this game!
Mike defeated his rivals
at Redemption.
He's got a skull,
and another skull.
That's five point for Michael.
To stay in the game.
And just like that,
Shannon is gone.
Shay really struggling.
Shay is gone.
Michael and Jak
are alive in this game.
Cementing his reputation
as a massive threat.
Love you guys. We'll see you
at tribal council.
Michael's been a form
player all the way through.
Can anyone beat Goliath?
When Jak lost the final
Redemption battle...
Jak has dropped.
Michael and Nate
are still in this game.
Mike and Nate lived to fight
another day at Casar.
It's either me or Mike.
He is a force coming back
into the game.
So for Mike
it was just the one day.
Michael heading for his tenth.
Michael drops.
As Tom won his most
crucial challenge yet.
Tom wins immunity!
And the tribe took out Goliath.
The eighth person
voted out of Casar is,
Mike.
- See ya later.
- Just four players
remained in Casar,
and once again
Barbs was confronted
with the tough decision.
It's been an emotional
roller-coaster for me,
- you know?
- Yeah.
To vote out her friend Nate,
or to bow out herself.
- You okay?
- Not really.
And provide a valuable jury vote
for her favorite, Avi.
Avi needs my vote.
He's not going to beat you
without me.
In the end...
Ninth person voted out
of Casar is,
Nate.
She decided to back herself,
and take a shot at the title.
And now
just three players remain.
Tom, the teacher from Tauranga
who thwarted elimination
and won immunity
when it mattered most.
Yeah, I can definitely win.
I've got a strategy in mind
that I think might work.
Avi, the youth expedition leader
from Wellington
who carefully navigated
through conflicting loyalties
and promises
to stay in the game.
I feel proud and happy
with the game I've played,
which is an amazing feeling
after thirty-seven days.
Barbara, horse owner and mother
from Auckland,
underestimated at first
- but pulled some big moves.
- Yeah!
To become a major player.
I am really proud
that I'm the oldest woman,
and I'm still here.
And I think that's going
to be really cool.
Really cool for my daughter.
Tonight our three finalists
put their case to the jury...
I want to know if you feel
you have been a kind person
in this game.
Some things you did
were really, really selfish.
I've never felt so belittled.
On the respect of those
that naturally respected you.
There is actually nothing
you could say at this point
which would make me
vote for you.
Who will decide
the one-hundred-thousand
dollar winner
and New Zealand's
first ever sole Survivor.
Wahoo.
Home sweet home
for one more night.
I know.
- This is it.
- Oh, man.
God. Final three.
Who would have thought?
Not me. Nope.
Congratulations you guys.
Ohh.
- Yeah.
- Bring it in.
Final three. Man,
what a journey.
- It's surreal.
- I know.
I can't take it in.
Oh my gosh,
what a crazy sort of...
Nate was really good, wasn't he?
- Ah yeah, of course.
- He's the man.
Writing Nate's name down
was really bittersweet for me,
because my name was going
to be written down.
And, honestly,
it was only half an hour
before we went to tribal
that we all came
to a mutual decision and it,
it was because of Nate.
He was adamant
I had to go to the end
and that I deserved it
and not to give up and...
and just think
what my eighteen-year-old
would think, you know.
So, I did, and he was right.
And actually, I think,
you know when you have a jury
you always have
the head juror. To me...
He'd be the one, aye.
So with Nate gone,
it means potentially
one less vote for me
in the jury.
I knew that Barb
was going to vote for me,
I'm not sure about Nate.
I know he got on
really well with Tom.
I don't think the jury's
looking very positive for me.
But hey, that's okay.
I don't think
they'll smile at me.
I feel
like there's a lot of room
at the final tribal, you know?
I feel like maybe
decisions are made
and opinions are already formed,
but I feel like on the night
they'll be quite like, um,
malleable.
- Yeah.
- Don't you reckon?
I think so. Yeah.
It's really good
to have a jury of your mates.
However, this isn't
your friend wins.
This is who's played
the best game,
and I know a lot of, um,
the guys
especially are going to be
looking at Tom's game
and his multiple immunity wins.
So it does make me nervous.
Oh, my gosh.
My feeling
it's going to be split
between myself and Avi.
I'm just going to have
to plead my case
best I can
and see who snags at it.
I can't believe
this is our last night!
- Oh, my God.
- It's so crazy.
-Honestly guys,
there's no one else I'd be...
- No.
- Wanting to share
- the final three with or...
- Really cool people.
This last night with.
I'm really happy to be sitting
beside my two friends
who I think totally deserve
to be here,
and will definitely give me
a run for the money.
Um, so I think it's going
to come down to a fight.
Good night
you legendary final three.
Here's to our last night
in Survivor.
Thirty-nine days is huge.
It's almost six weeks
out here in the jungle
on the beach,
which makes it sound
like paradise, which it is.
But it's been no easy stroll.
It's been hard.
It's been really hard.
Yeah, way better today.
It'll be the last time
I'm looking at it.
Yeah.
I don't think I've
stepped out of the game once.
I don't think I've stopped
thinking about the game once.
So its relief knowing
that tonight it's over,
and I've done
everything that I can do
to get to this point.
Day thirty-nine
and down to bones.
Skin and bones, you know,
just want to get
a good meal in me.
This has been such a huge dream
of mine for such a long time.
I used to be obsessed with
Survivor through high school.
I used to make my friends
do Survivor challenges.
So to be here,
and to be in the final three,
is honestly
a dream come true for me.
I think a huge, huge step
of winning this game
is tonight's tribal council.
I know that there's
a lot of people on that jury
who haven't made up
their mind at all,
by any means.
Tonight I'm really just
gonna have to prove to them
how hard I've fought,
and kind of the type of game
that I've played.
And it's a game
that I'm proud of,
and I'm proud of who
I've been in this game.
I'm just going to
have to let them know that,
and let them see it,
and let them come to
the conclusion
that I deserve
to be the sole Survivor.
It's nerve-racking,
but I trust them.
I trust them to make
the best decision they know.
I definitely think
that I deserve
to be the winner
of this competition.
- Wa-yaho.
- Oh, nice mat.
- Eh, what the...
- Pretty mat.
- Ohh!
- Oh, yo!
Ohh! Oh, bread.
- Oh, my God.
- Bun. Look at these!
- What is this?
- Oh, doughnuts!
What is this going to be?
Eggs. Bacon.
Oh, my... Oh, my God.
They've given us a pan.
Oh, my God, butter.
Oh, my God, they're so fresh.
- Ready? Cheers.
- Cheers guys.
Final three.
Mmm. Oh, my God.
Something's happening
to my tummy.
It's telling me something,
but I'm just ignoring it.
- It can leave me alone.
- Yeah.
The stomachs just like,
"What are you doing? Again?"
I thought we were sorted man.
Yeah, "I thought we'd
been through this already."
Rice and beans.
I'm feeling
much better this morning,
and feeling in a good place.
And as long...
as I don't think too much
about my family I'll be fine.
So, um, yeah.
I'll be good.
I hope.
'Cause I don't
want to cry tonight.
I'll be good.
I'll be fine. I'll be fine.
Um, but I'm feeling
really good and I...
Every so often I'll smile
and think I can't believe
I'm here
and, um,
it's going to be so cool.
Because I won't tell the kids,
and they'll...
I'll just let them
watch the episodes
and it'll be really cool
that they'll have no idea
their mother got this far.
And I think it's really neat.
Oh, that's yummy.
All I've done for 27 years
is all been a girlfriend,
a wife, a mother,
and I said this time I don't
want to think about anyone
and I just want
to think about me.
Ohh, yeah. Doughnut.
Doughnuts.
It was a real selfish
kinda personal odyssey for me
and that's why I looked at
Survivor differently
to a lot of other players.
They were just gunning
for the money in the end.
I kinda was using this
as my eat-pray-love journey.
I came to challenge myself
for myself.
If I was watching this program,
I know who I'd vote for,
and it would be me.
And I'm not just saying that,
I would just do it
from principle
of seeing this woman
who's 27 years older
and still holding her own.
I've had my heat, exhaustion,
and I've worked through it.
I'm not going for $100,000,
I'm going as if
I want my children
when they watch it
to be proud of what I say.
So, that's how I see it.
Sorry.
I don't need to sell myself.
I know what I am and my worth,
and I don't need to do that
for anyone
and if they can't
recognize my potential
then that's their loss.
My way of approaching it
is giving a life lesson
to my children in how you...
how you play a game
like this on TV.
What a good last feast, aye?
Yeah.
Are you feeling anxious at all?
- About tonight?
- Nah, yeah.
- Oh, you are?
- Yeah.
Oh, my gosh.
- You guys.
- Did you smell the bacon?
You could be like
the outdoor shed.
The Survivor Outdoor,
you need to...
you need to do yours cookbook.
Survivor cook book.
First meal on it,
rice and beans.
Yeah, yeah. Yeah.
"Thirty-nine days
of how to cook rice and beans,
thirty-nine different ways."
There you go.
That could be your title.
Thirty-nine days
out here is nuts.
The thing that got me here,
all the way to day 39,
was keeping head strong.
Winning challenges was not
actually what was going on,
it was what I had
going through my head and,
you know, knowing that
it's not over till it's over
and just really using
my brain a bit more.
Hey guys, got to do the tree.
Oh, yeah. Keep Nate's
little mark in there.
- Use this one?
- Yeah.
Oh, no, you can.
I'll just sit there.
Where's the hammer?
I watched the original Survivor
when I was a boy
and loved it to pieces
and to think that I'd even
get a shot at the show,
let alone make it this far
is just... something else.
Final three as an achievement
is massive.
Should do an A, a B, and a T.
- Okay.
- Or B.A.T.
- Bat?
- Bat.
Now I've been thinking past it,
and now I've been thinking
to sole Survivor
and how I can plead my case.
Bat was here.
It's the Batrio.
Yeah.
I think the thing
that I'm worried about
is that Avi may soak up
some votes
from bringing me in,
and people thinking that
he carried me
those last few meters
over the line.
All right. We made our...
we made our mark.
Bat. Bat ass.
- All right.
- Oh, well, gotta pack.
- Pack up.
- Yeah.
I don't really wanna
destroy this place.
- Nah, let's leave it.
- It's been home for too long.
Yeah. Just get
our clothes out, aye?
And we'll go and sit
and have a think.
Yeah. Pack our bags.
We'll leave that.
It'll be a cool thing
for someone to stumble across.
Be like, "What the?"
Tonight at tribal
I'm just going to
lay out my story.
Tell them just
a few straight facts
about how the game actually
was going on in my view
and I think I've got
a few friends on the jury
as well as people
who will respect the game
- that I've played.
- All right.
Let's get ready.
Farewell camp.
And just really hope
that they take on me
as the one
who's the most deserving.
- Don't look back!
- Yeah.
Yeah, I can definitely win.
We'll now bring in
the members of our jury,
Lee, Sala,
Shannon, Shay,
Jak, Michael,
and Nate.
Ohh.
Tom, Avi, and Barbs,
you have done
what thirteen others
couldn't do in this game.
You've made it to the end.
Tonight though the power
shifts to the jury.
The seven people
you've voted out
will decide
who they think is worthy
of the title of "Sole Survivor,"
and the $100,000 prize.
You will have the chance
to make an opening statement.
It is your opportunity
to plead your case
and say why you deserve to win.
And then the jury
has a chance to address you,
to get some information
to make
a very important decision.
We'll then go to the vote.
Tom, you're up first.
This is something
that a lot of us have had
in our minds as something
we've been excited about
for however long,
and I've been excited about
the prospect since I was a kid.
I built up stories of Survivor
and I treated them
as these amazing people
off in this wondrous land.
I live my life as a role model
for a group of young people,
and so I could be
that person for them,
and that's what
I've had in my mind
through this whole game.
I wanted to play it honorably
and I wanted to go as hard
as I possibly could
till it just sucked me dry.
I wanted to get to that point,
see how far I could push myself
and I think
I've accomplished that.
I wanted to get to the very end,
and know that I earnt it.
Give me your questions
and I'll give you back
my honesty,
and I'll just tell you my story
and I hope you can respect me.
Thanks, Tom.
Avi, you're up.
Hey guys.
As most of you know
I'm a trip leader
and an overseas educator,
and before we head out
into the field
I sit my students down
and we write down
our intentions.
So I did the same thing
before coming out here.
And what were my intentions?
Like Tom, it was
to leave nothing on the field.
To give everything
that I had to this game.
I wanted to keep
my integrity intact.
I wanted to be honest.
I wanted to make connections.
Today when I look back
on my journal
I realize that
I'd fulfilled my intentions,
I really had.
You guys have the incredibly
daunting task of, uh,
choosing a winner tonight,
and I want you to know
I trust you.
In this situation,
I trust you completely.
Barbs. Your turn.
I'd like to say, firstly,
that I have achieved
my greatest challenge
in Survivor,
and that is
to sit in front of you
rather than sitting beside you.
I was a lone Survivor
right from the start.
I had some big egos
and big personalities
in my Hermosa tribe.
I had a bond with Nate
because he was
a like-minded person
going through
the same tribe as me.
For twelve days
I felt like dead man walking,
I had a noose around my neck.
I wasn't prepared to just
suck up
and sell myself to you guys
just so you'd keep me around.
I started playing on day 12
when we blended the tribe,
and suddenly
I sat up and thought,
"Oh, I'm not just a lioness
waiting in the grass
looking at a herd of people
all flock together.
Now the people
I can start picking off
because you're
moving out of the tribe."
I made the biggest move,
I feel, in Survivor,
taking out Sala.
And that was all on me.
Everyone jumped on board.
I feel I played
with a velvet glove.
I've been really
subtle with my play.
You underestimated me,
you overlooked me
and that suited
my purposes actually.
I think I'm here
because you overlooked me.
You were so busy
targeting each other
and thinking
of the obvious threats,
you just let me
come up the middle,
pop up and go back down.
I'm here
because of your inability
to be perceptive enough to see
that I actually
am quite strategic.
I'm really wrapped that
I'm the last female here,
and the oldest one in the game,
and I think I will be
an inspiration
to a lot of people.
Thank you Barbs.
The jury, finally,
after 39 long days in this game,
you now have a chance to
address Tom, Avi, and Barbs.
You're looking for information
to make $100,000 decision.
Shay, you're up first.
- Hi, guys.
- Hey, Shay.
I have a question
for each of you.
Um, Barb,
I want to know
if you feel you have been
a kind person in this game.
I don't think I've treated
anyone disrespectfully.
If I don't have
anything nice to say
I just don't say anything.
Yeah, I would say
I've been kind.
Okay. Cool. Thank you.
- Avi. Hi.
- Hi.
You know that I love you.
My question Avi is,
"What do you think
the youth of New Zealand
can learn from the way
that you've played your game?"
I think that
treating people well
can get you far.
Just by being respectful,
by being kind,
I think can go
a really long way.
Awesome, thank you.
Hi, Tom. We have a bit
of a head-butting history
in this game.
I want to clear
the air between us.
I feel like there was a point
where a line had been crossed
and I refuse to hear
and see my name
be dragged through the mud.
If you haven't said
a horrible thing about me
then I sincerely apologize
and there are some liars
in the jury.
If you have anything
you'd like to say to me,
I would love for you
to take that opportunity.
When you talk about, you know,
dragging someone's name
through the mud,
I heard back to me stuff
that I'd kind of
consider the same.
But that's not the way
I feel about you.
There is nothing personal
in this, no vengeance.
Nothing against
your character as a person.
I thought that your gameplay
was just intense,
and a lot of it was
because it was,
you know, coming at me.
I really respect that.
Thank you for clarifying
that for me.
Jak. Come on up.
I don't have
a question for any of you,
I made my decision last night.
What I have to say
to each of you
is the honest truth.
I'm going to start with you Avi.
So I start out
the game thinking,
"This guy is too nice
to be real.
I cannot believe you,
this is just a fraud.
This is a fake."
But you proved to me
that you are as honest
and as close to being perfect
as you can be,
and I'm so stoked that
you've made it here bro.
Ten out of ten.
And Tom bro.
I never thought I'd make
such an awesome friend
out here bro.
You helped me through a lot bro
and I'm just real grateful.
Barb,
I respect that
you have come out here
and you've given it
a good crack.
You exceeded
my expectations of you.
You did really, really well
at challenges,
but that's as far
as it goes for me.
We spoke a lot about
respect and maturity,
and I don't know
if what you did for me
could earn my respect.
But I feel like
some things you did
were really, really selfish
and you felt
a little bit entitled,
like you deserved our respect.
And I don't know about that.
And there was times
when it was raining,
we needed the mats
to sleep on the ground.
And it's a small thing,
and it might sound petty,
but it felt like
you would rather
us sleep on the dirt.
It felt like just because
you were older than us,
you had a sadder story
or a better story
and, like, if that's not true
it's whatever,
this is how I feel
and I'm telling you
- how I feel.
- Its okay.
So if you disagree
with it it's cool.
I felt like you were
condescending at times,
and that was sort of
the age thing as well.
It's like you spoke
to us like we were children.
I should have told you this
at the time,
and I feel like a coward
for not doing that,
but 'cause I'm speaking
from my heart
and that's what
I want to do from now on.
I've learnt that from Avi.
I've learnt that from Sala.
I've learnt that from Shay.
I've learnt that from Nate.
If we can all take something
from this game
and become better people,
for me that is a bit more
than $100,000.
If you don't take
any of that on-board
then I'm not sure
about how I can feel
about you as a person.
Thanks, Jak. Michael.
No, no it's fine.
Barbara...
I agree with pretty much
everything Jak just said,
so I'm not going to point out
any of those points again.
All right, Avi,
I wanna vote for someone
that truly deeply wants
to win this game,
and I feel like Tom
wants to win this game
a lot more than you.
Convince me otherwise.
All right, Avi,
I want to vote for someone
that truly deeply wants
to win this game,
and I feel like Tom
wants to win this game
a lot more than you.
Convince me otherwise.
Every single day I wrote down,
"You can do this,
you can do this."
Like half of what I as writing
out on those rocks
was a massive pep-talk to myself
to make it to the end,
to keep fighting.
I don't know if I've ever wanted
something more in my life.
Cheers, thanks.
Tom, I want to vote for someone
that has solid character,
good morals,
and a winner that New Zealand
can look at
and be like,
"They're an awesome person."
Avi, he's easily got
all those qualities.
Convince me that you've also
got those qualities as well.
Every day I wake up ecstatic
about changing the lives
of a group
of what I call my own,
and that's where
I want to make my major mark.
You know, I have had
struggles in my life
and there's been people
to help me through it
and some of those people
were teachers
and I want everyone to be
the best person they can be.
That's all I'm trying to do
just in my day-to-day.
Awesome, thanks.
Nate, you're up.
Congratulations. Well done,
I'm proud of you all.
I've only got one question.
Day 35, that's when
I was voted out the first time.
Avi, we talked a lot
about final three stuff
and was always me,
you, and someone else.
I want to know
when the plan changed
and why you never had
that courageous conversation
with me.
Um, I feel like I kept
coming up and being like,
"Nate how about final three?"
But I guess I just didn't get
that commitment back.
Yeah, but I tried.
Okay. Thanks.
Shannon, your turn.
All righty.
Barb, I don't have
a question for you tonight
because, to be honest,
there is actually nothing
you could say at this point
which would make me
vote for you.
Avi, do you honestly believe
that just being a nice person
is enough to win Survivor?
I have been kind of painted
with this brush
of just being the nice guy.
But I worked so hard
to get here,
and it definitely
wasn't just by being nice.
I had to save myself
a number of times,
you know, as Mogoton
was getting chipped away at,
when Sala was voted out
and my entire game plan
got smashed to the ground.
I've worked really hard,
and I've had to play
every single aspect
of this game to stay in it.
Thanks Avi.
And Tom, there have been
so many times
where you were this close
to being voted out
and the reason
that you stayed in the game,
I heard, was because Avi
has saved you.
Do you think that you
would still be sitting there
if it wasn't for Avi?
Any alliance has
a two-way combo that you need
as the need is wanted back.
So if you're thinking
about it as I needed him,
you've also got to turn it back
and say how did Avi need me?
Cool. Thank you.
Thanks Shannon.
Sala, you're up.
Big ups, 39 days, final three.
Mad props and respect,
uh, from me to you,
so congratulations.
Tom, I can honestly say my bro
that your students,
your mum, your dad,
your closest friends and family
will be bloody proud
of you, bro,
and how you've played the game.
So well done.
Avi, it's bloody great
to see that nice guys
can make it to the final three.
Barbara, AKA Mumma B.
Respect is reciprocated,
uh, when it's given.
My observation of you, Barbara,
is that you're kind of
the opposite of respectful.
What I saw was disrespect.
We had a shelter,
and half of it
was occupied by you.
You did very little
in camp life,
camp environment, camp culture
in my opinion, just observation.
You complained a lot about,
oh, everything and everyone.
What really hurt me,
uh, Momma B was
on the respect
of those that naturally
respected you.
So my last Korero
to you Momma B is,
"All the best."
Lee.
One more. One more.
One more roasting.
Hey guys.
You know there's so many ways
this game could have been
played out,
and for me
I'd like to really entertain
that a major contributor to,
like, what's gotten you here
is luck, possibly.
What I want to know,
just a simple yes-no answer,
is, "if you had no good luck
laid upon you,
would you still be
sitting there right now?"
Tom?
Yes.
Avi?
Barb?
No.
Cool. Cheers 2.
Good one to end on.
All right guys,
you've had your opportunity
to address the final three.
You've heard their responses.
It is now time to vote.
Remember, tonight
you are voting for the person
you want to win the very first
Survivor New Zealand.
The person you want to see
take away
the $100,000.
For the final time,
it is time to vote.
Nate, you're up first.
Bro, you're the best mate
I've had out here.
You absolutely deserve this
110%.
I'm very proud to have journeyed
the first Survivor
with a man like you.
I'll get the votes.
Tom, Avi, Barbs,
everyone on the jury,
thank you so much for
a great season of Survivor.
One of you has just won
$100,000.
See you back in New Zealand
on day forty
when I tell you the votes.
All right. Thank you everyone.
Thanks for
an incredible welcome.
Guys, how are you doing?
Good.
Are we all right?
Yeah!
All right.
Lou, nice to see you back.
How's your health?
Oh, fabulous thank you.
Good. Looking stunning.
Oh, why thank you. You too!
Stop it! Stop it!
Ah, Jak nice to see you
with some clothes on tonight.
Hey!
I thought I'd do everyone
a favor for once eh.
I did want to wear it but uh,
there was a bit
of potential repercussions.
Oh, is that right?
For revealing the crack!
Are you modeling yet or not?
No. I need to wax first.
I'm still covered
Right, okay.
So, for our first season
of Survivor New Zealand
we wanted a great cast.
You guys delivered in spades.
We loved...
We loved following your game,
so thanks for an amazing
first season.
But now, it all comes down
to Tom, Barb and Avi.
Tommy, how are the nerves?
Mate!
Just wild eh.
- Yeah?
- Yeah.
We've spent ages backstage
just hearing this kind of
sound of...
And we're like,
"Get us out there!"
Barb, how excited are you about
being back together
after all this time?
Ah, a little bit of trepidation.
But, um, it's good.
Good closure.
Great. Well, this is
what this is all about.
Avi, watching back now,
what was the hardest thing
about playing this game?
Oh, there were
so many elements of it
which were...
which were difficult.
Um, I think it was just
kind of that, um,
underlying paranoia
that was simmering away
all the time.
You know,
you were never really sure
of where you stood
or what was about to happen.
Um, so just kind of
being on edge the whole time,
that was really difficult
thing to spend 39 days doing.
Yeah,
well we're about to find out
how it's all panned out.
After 39 days
of tough decisions,
the big question is
"Did you three
make the right decisions
along the way?
Have you put people
on the jury who think
you deserve it the most?"
It's time to find out.
It's time to read the votes.
Shall we do this?
Okay.
First vote...
Avi.
Second vote...
Tom.
One vote Avi, one vote Tom.
Third vote...
Are you guys nervous?
- Nah, I'm fine this is great.
- I'm nervous.
Third vote...
Avi.
Two votes Avi,
one vote Tom.
Fourth vote...
Avi.
Three votes Avi,
one vote Tom.
Look at your face!
Smile! Smile! Smile! Come on!
The winner of
Survivor New Zealand
and the $100,000 is Avi!
Avi, you did it!
You did it!
I'm so proud of you.
- I love you.
Good job bro.
Well done, brother.
- Avi, you did it!
- Righto guys.
Hang on guys.
- Take your seats please.
- You proved everyone wrong.
Proud of you.
Guys, please take your seats.
Avi, well done.
I'm so happy for you.
I've got to chat to this man.
I've gotta chat to this man.
Give me a hug.
- Thank you.
- I know.
Shot brother.
Are we sitting down here?
Righto guys, let's go.
Avi, how good
are you feeling brother?
Oh
Oh my God. Um...
oh, this is... this is...
this is a dream come true
and, um, yeah, I just...
I'm so grateful.
This is such a bizarre,
incredible experience
and I love you all so much
and we're all just going to be
in each other's life forever,
you know.
This was amazing!
These guys are amazing!
Um...
Avi,
anyone you want to see
out in that crowd?
Uh, yeah!
Get down there brother!
Cheers cuzzies.
Cheers guys.
Mom.
Sophia's here.
Oh my God.
I know.
I just won Survivor.
Against...
Excuse me, I'm really
sorry to break you up.
Oh, that's fine.
You must be Mom?
I am Mom, yeah.
Yes, I am Mom.
How proud are you right now?
I am so proud of him.
He played with such integrity.
I was a little bit worried
that that wasn't going to do it,
but it did it!
Tell me, has...
has your Avi always
been this nice?
- Yes!
- Oh yeah, obviously!
He just...
He was just who he was.
He was a hundred percent Avi.
- That's him?
- Yup!
Remarkable.
We saw that from
day one actually.
Yup, yup, yup.
Well, you should be very proud.
I am so proud!
Enjoy, enjoy, enjoy.
How are you feeling?
All right.
After the break,
she woke from her slumber
to take a serious shot
at the title,
we're talking to Barbs
then later,
the GEM People's Choice Award.
You don't want to miss it!
Thank you.
Smile! Smile!
Smile! Come on.
The winner
of Survivor New Zealand
and the $100,000 is Avi!
Welcome back
to the Survivor New Zealand
Live Final,
where Avi has just won $100,000.
Avi, again, congratulations.
Has it sunk in yet?
Um, no, no.
This is some weird dreamscape
that I'm just going to snap
out of at some stage.
Okay, well, we're going
to talk more to you later.
Now let's get back
to our final three
and one of the more
interesting aspects
of the season.
Sitting here is the best
physical player in Tom,
the best strategic player
in Barb
and the best social player
in Avi.
Take a look at this clip.
I think I can win
because I'm very perceptive
and I think socially I can
pick up on a lot of things.
I think I have
a little mantra in my head
and that will be, "Need must
as the devil drives".
Everyone, you know,
they have their principles
but sometimes circumstances
make you go against those.
So, that is what may happen.
Yeah, I think I can win Survivor.
I feel like I am an all-rounder
in terms of physical
and mental and being composed.
Welcome to Nikoragua.
What did you think
of Barbs idea?
- It's big.
- It's like a chess set
and I can just see
which way to move somebody
or say something.
I think she put up
a hit on my head.
Definitely behind
the hit on my head.
Queen me, darling.
Queen me!
The biggest threat is Avi.
He is one of the most liked
people in the game.
I feel good about
the relationships
that I've made with the jury.
I feel really close to
every single person up there.
Tom has won, again!
Tom wins immunity.
It is concerning for me
the more immunity's he wins.
His argument at the end
will be stronger.
Tom, you are unbeatable
and I'm sure for the others
that is unbearable.
Okay.
Avi, it was always
going to be interesting
watching Kiwis
and see how they played
and responded to the game.
The three of you had
different strengths
but essentially Avi you needed
all three game plays to win, eh?
Yeah, I was a bit nervous,
um, during the end
when I realized that,
you know,
I was the nice guy, you know?
I was like...
I feel like I have played
in all areas of the game
you know.
I was very, um,
present throughout
and, um, kind of, you know,
I really put it all out there.
But yeah, I think
you do need all facets,
um, to win I guess.
I think you're right.
Okay, well of the three
game plays,
the hardest for Kiwis
to stomach was strategy.
Barb went from dead man
walking to mafia queen.
Take a look.
Our tribe is divided.
We know that us five are solid.
We need to throw
the next immunity challenge.
That could come back
and bite us in the butt.
I was dead man walking
waiting for the axe to fall.
We're redrawing for new tribes.
The tide has turned.
Feeling like, oh, I think
I'm starting Survivor tomorrow.
What a great position
to be in though, eh?
As you sow, you shall reap.
Lee.
Michael. The tribe has spoken.
That was a double bonanza.
I now can start using
my powers of perception
to break up the Shay, Avi
and Sala threesome.
Way.
At one point,
she was the old Labrador
sitting on the porch
but now she's a little
pippy fox terrier
running around the front yard.
Sala.
You are underestimated.
I know everyone
has underestimated me.
Barbs is a definite
concern for me.
She started off zero threat.
Jak, the tribe has spoken.
Shannon.
Shay.
I'm like a lioness
looking at my prey.
If she goes with the two guys
that have been carrying her,
she'll get zero votes.
For somebody
that's being carried,
I seem to be a linch pin
a hell of a lot in this game.
Mike.
You need to bring me your torch.
Yeah, I think
I'm quite inspirational
for a lot of people.
Especially being totally kind
of isolated at the beginning.
So yeah, I'd be routing for me.
I deserve it.
Barb, brutal but beautiful.
Hermosa!
I want to talk to you
about that final tribal,
have you recovered?
Uh, to be honest,
I didn't watch it just then.
I thought once was enough
over there.
So, no need to see it again.
The six-pack mauling
that I received.
I would say they're really lucky
that it was edited
and condensed down
because it was far more brutal
than that
and far more was said.
Uh, and my decision
for going to final three,
I have to be honest,
I never considered
any of their votes.
They were irrelevant to me.
My strategy...
They were just pawns so...
- You did it for you!
- Yup. Basically.
Avi, in many ways Barb enabled
you and Tom to get to the end.
Are you comfortable
with the beating she took
as you guys sat by?
No, of course not.
It was... It was really rough
on that final tribal
and, you know, part of me does
beat myself up a little bit.
Um, I wish I could of
or would have said something.
Avi, why didn't you jump in?
I think we were kind of,
um, maneuvering
in that weird space
of self-preservation
and we're all terrified
to even be there, you know,
we're like, "I hope everyone
likes me", you know, like...
So, you know I was hearing
what was being said
and it was harsh. It was.
Um, but I think that kind of
self-preservation kicked in
and I do... I do regret
not kind of saying something
but also at the time
it seemed impossible.
Tom, do you think the jury
was fair to Barb?
I think that there was, uh...
There was a mixture
of fair and unfair comments
and, um, I think
the unfair comments
actually didn't get much light.
Um, no light.
I think the stuff
that came across
as people were treated,
like Jak said
that maybe the way
he was treated, you know.
I did actually... You know,
I saw cases like that.
Um, you know
but there were other cases
where it was personal,
it wasn't so much about
the game that she'd played.
It was really...
It was a dig at maybe,
you know, her personality
and who she was.
Do you want to shed
some more light on that?
- Yeah, okay, well...
- Let's do it.
- Now that we're here.
Like... And...
I don't want it to be, you know,
I don't want this to be,
you know, me calling out
people in any bitter ways
it's like, we all just lost
to the guy
that was just as deserving
to anyone else here.
Yeah.
Um, but, you know
there was comments, like,
Sala you referred to Barb
as a... as a turd in the toilet
that wouldn't flush.
You know, and that's...
Some people take that
as really harsh.
There were other comments
like Shannon you said like...
- Go back to my knitting!
- Yeah.
- Shame on you!
- Sala.
Sala, you did say that.
What was shown was just
a snippet of what you said.
You've later said that you
respected Barb and her game.
Do you think
that you respected her
in that final tribal?
Um...
I still respect Barb.
Did you in that final tribal?
I think I needed to share
what was going on for me
at that time.
Um, at the end of the day,
people can choose
how to interpret what we say.
I mean, yup, I did say that,
um, she was a,
you know a turd that was
floating in the toilets
refused to be flushed
but at the end of the day,
you know, we all got flushed
and she was still there
and so...
In some kind of whacky way...
It was a...
It was a sign of respect say
that she...
These guys were still there
and I was flushed bro.
I was down the drain. Gone.
Somewhere over there.
Would you say that again,
given another chance?
I think... You know, you...
We were all under pressure,
um...
and watching it again,
Barb played an amazing game.
She was bloody good...
and you know, so...
I am pretty gutted,
because she pulled up Mike
for being arrogant
with his korero to her
and yeah, respectively so,
and then she goes
and does that same to us
with her pitch.
So, I was kind of confused
at the end,
that's when I ended up
wanting to share,
actually no this is...
So, you think some of it
was deserving?
Um, at that time, yup.
- Yup.
- Shannon...
Shannon,
Tom also referred to you.
What do you make of what
you said in that final tribal?
I mean, I'm kind of the same
as Sala.
After watching the show,
I think she played a better game
than I gave her credit for
at the time.
But at the same time,
she clearly was lacking
the social game,
like I was as well,
which is why, you know,
I ended up here.
But, the fact that six of us
had the same opinion,
I mean, that is
a big aspect of Survivor,
which she was lacking in.
So, I mean,
we were just speaking honestly
at that point.
- From what we had experience.
- Fair comment.
All right, after the break,
Tom's game is next.
You don't want to miss it.
You're back live
at Auckland's Civic
for the Survivor New Zealand
final.
Now, he was mentally
and physically
the strongest player
in the game.
In challenges,
he was unstoppable.
Let's look at Tom's ride
to the final three.
Last person
left standing wins' immunity.
Winning immunity
when I've needed it
has been my game plan
and I have been able
to pull it off.
Survivor's ready.
Survivors ready!
Hands off in three...
two... one...
For immunity, go!
Tom, first out of the blocks.
Putting a little bit
of water into that container.
Tom thinks he's got it.
That was quick.
Tom, has won
individual immunity!
Tom's got five medallions.
He wins immunity!
Tom, match point for him.
Again, Tom wins immunity.
Oh, my God, Tom again.
He's been epic, hasn't he?
He's just been the full player
and he's won them convincingly.
Avi, gone.
Nate is gone, so is Shay.
Barb is gone.
Tom wins immunity, again.
If there was anyone
in the game I needed
to beat it needed to be Mike.
So, I've finally got my shot.
I really want it.
Michael placing his ninth now.
Tom about to place his tenth.
Three... two... one!
Tom wins immunity.
Me winning will be
a reflection of the game
I've played and a part
of that is being really strong
in challenges
when I've needed it.
Yeah, I can definitely win.
Tommy, little plug here,
as you know we both
went to Waitaki Boys
in Oamaru and I'm really proud
of you, mate!
You were a seriously
strong contender.
But, when it came time
to plead your case
at that final tribal,
did you choke a little?
Yeah, it definitely
came to that.
I think... I think
I was pretty weak in the end.
I didn't give... I should
have just gone bang bang bang
"I did this, you put me
in a corner
"and I got out" um...
Yeah, I think you missed
an opportunity
to show the jury just how good
your social and strategic game
actually was.
Cause you were fighting
for your life
from day one almost.
Yeah, I had this ridiculous...
Well, not ridiculous...
I had this idea that you know,
the... As people went out
the story was kind of told
and that I was just there
to kind of, um,
be open to answering
their questions
and I just misread
that at the last moment
and I just didn't read
the instructions right.
It might have been something
about that school, Tommy.
While... While we are
all talking about it.
Who did vote for Tom?
I did!
- Jaky!
- Woo!
And I'd vote for him
a thousand times over.
I'd vote for him every day
of the week.
A little bit of a man crush, eh?
A man crush?
I don't know.
It's like
a full-blown relationship.
You heard it here first.
So, Tom, just Jak, what happened
to the rest
of the boy band votes?
Ask them.
Yeah, I mean, I can ask them...
I mean, what happened?
Like, I, you know,
I obviously didn't give
what was needed but
from your point of view, why?
He's talking to you buddy!
Uh, well, I guess for me, uh,
there was nothing that Tom did
at all that made me
not vote for him,
it was more Avi.
It was...
Mikey, do you want...
Do you wanna tell us
how you're spelling that?
Do you know, I thought
the entire game
his name was spelt R and then V.
- Seriously?
- Yup.
Like he was some sort
of cool cat.
Yup!
I thought
he was a motor transport.
Oh, wow, Mike!
Nah, but like, Avi he...
A-V-I, Avi, yeah, he...
The reason I voted for him
basically was because, yeah,
I've...
And everyone
who knows who's pretty much
been in the presence of Avi
that there's...
There's barely any people
in the world
that you meet that
just when you talk to them
they're just the most genuine,
kind people ever
and for example I've only met
two in my life
and they are both sitting
on this stage...
Avi and Sala...
And they're both
just the most amazing people.
I think you're probably right.
Do you have a little tear
in your eye now?
Definitely not, no.
- Camera on Mike right now.
- Get away, get away.
And Lee, your take?
Another boy band member,
your take on that.
Yeah, yeah.
Me and Mike
had a pretty similar thought
process I think.
Um, I was completely undecided
even when I actually had
the pen in my hand,
before I was about to write...
Straight up.
I should have just asked him
to pick a number
between one and ten
because that's... Yeah,
but what it came down to for me
and after I was thinking
and, yeah...
If... It was basically
Tom just spanked out
the challenges
and that was epic, um,
and Avi he played an epic
social game and not once
did it feel like he was
on the chopping block.
It felt like he had
a lot of cards in his hands.
He had control
of the game the whole time.
Um, I think if Avi didn't win
that last challenge,
then he would have had less
for me to give him
I think and, um, and,
just what he gave...
His final words that he gave
was completely convincing.
- I couldn't yeah...
- Absolutely.
Having watched the show,
would any of, you now,
vote differently?
Good honesty Nate.
Why's that?
Um, I just, uh,
I didn't vote for Tom
but having seen
where he came from...
from Mogoton
back against the wall.
Um, he came over with the merge,
back against the wall,
um, and yup he had to win
the challenges at the start.
But he traded his way
I thought socially for me
that he didn't have to win.
You know,
and it proved at the end
that he didn't have to win
that last challenge.
But I think
he had socially had it
in, you know, uh,
in the bag as well.
He was safe from elimination
if he didn't win
those immunities,
those challenges.
I just... I think they are all
absolutely totally worthy.
I just... Yeah,
I thought that was great.
Thanks, Nate and thanks Tommy.
Without a doubt...
Without a doubt Tom
was the strongest player
in the game
but there was another force
to be reckoned with out
of the game...
The Mighty Goliath.
Second person voted out
of Casar...
Michael.
Somehow, found myself
on Redemption Island,
which really sucks.
This is going to get up
to somewhere like 32,
33 I'd say, before
I can get back in the game.
I said, "What the plan
Michael?",
he said, "To win everyone".
Michael is sweet
and stays alive in this game,
And another skull.
That's five points for Michael
who stays alive in this game.
And just like that,
Shannon is gone.
He's proved himself
to be the ultimate competitor.
Shay is gone.
Michael and Jak are alive
in this game.
Well guys...
it is time...
to head back
to Redemption Island.
Oh, my gosh.
Michael's been the form
player all the way through.
Can anyone beat Goliath?
And Jak has dropped.
Michael and Nate
are still in this game.
Mike it's time for you
to rejoin your old tribe.
Mikey, uh,
the look on your face,
priceless mate.
Oh, yeah, that was...
I can't believe
you did that man.
I can't take it back.
It's happened, hasn't it?
- It has.
- Okay.
Hey look, um, I think
the difference between you
and Avi, for example,
was he knew Survivor
was a dynamic game
and he was always checking in
with people.
Was your tight five
your only strategy?
Oh, at that point,
I guess, it was.
There was that tight five.
I could also see there
was people in the other tribe
that I'd potentially get
along with if there
was some kind of tribe swap,
which is what happened,
and, yeah...
Were you too trusting
of your original alliance?
As we saw played out,
obviously, I was, yes.
Um, yeah, yeah,
obviously, I was, yeah.
Sweet.
Uh...
now Georgia, some people think
the tight five
was perhaps too confident,
arrogant even.
Would you play differently
given another crack?
Okay, I do not class
us as arrogant at all.
We were in the numbers...
There were five of us,
so, yeah,
at the start of Survivor,
the thing is
you want to feel comfortable.
You want to be in the numbers,
that's the main thing.
Um, and, yeah, we were
a strong tribe and, yeah,
we won those challenges
and we actually didn't have
to think about
who we were voting off next.
We didn't have to do
all those horrible talks.
So, we were actually
having a really lovely time
and we totally tried
to include people
as much as we could and, yeah...
Could you have been
nicer to Barb and Nate?
I think, um, personally, um,
I wasn't at all horrible to them
and they weren't horrible
to me and, yeah,
I think, um...
I think it was...
Okay and now this, uh,
off subject and time
is of the essence but,
you know, this is coming Mike,
everyone wants to know,
what really went down
between you and Georgia?
Do you want me to step in here?
Yeah.
It's funny because I think
I actually have
a better perspective
on the whole thing,
because I was at the bottom
- of the...
- You were watching!
No, I was at the bottom
of the bed
when they were spooning
every night
and so I could...
Jak, you were spooning...
You were spooning
my feet in the night, dude.
Don't you forget that.
But and then Mikey would come in
for like an hour or two,
have a little cuddle...
You could hear them whispering
and then he'd shimmy off out
to the beach and go to sleep.
And that's what happened, Mike?
Not at all.
Nah, so...
Was your relationship physical?
All right, all right, hold on,
all right.
I think I've got some
damage control to do now.
Um, no, so yeah... Survivor.
We had an awesome relationship
on Survivor.
We totally trusted each other.
Lots of fun.
Shared lots of experiences.
-It was all friendship
-Bro!
Choose your words!
It was all...
It was all experiences.
It was all a great friendship
and I think it's going to last
for a long time.
Yeah, it's great.
It's purely a friendship.
- Bro, just leave it.
- Just leave it at that.
- Go to the commercial.
- Let's go
to the... He wants to go
to the commercial.
After the break,
when all is said and done,
nice guys can win Survivor.
We're back with Avi.
You don't want to miss it!
Welcome back
to the Civic in Auckland
and our live final.
Earlier, Avi took out
the title of New Zealand's
first ever sole survivor
and the $100,000
that goes with it.
Look at how he got there.
Who would you trust
with your life?
He's the world's nicest man.
Everyone likes Avi.
A lot of people with Avi.
His social game
is really, really good.
Pinky swear.
I do feel really good
that I'm forging
these really tight relationships
with every single person
in my tribe.
Tomorrow, another one goes
and it's for sure not us.
I feel like tonight is
going to go pretty smoothly.
We've all agreed it's Jak.
Third person voted out
of Casar is...
Sala.
I feel like such a fool.
I thought I could just be nice
and trusting
but I guess that's not how
this stupid game goes.
In an effort to save myself
after Sala left,
I made sure that I was part
of every single conversation
and every single
potential alliance
that was going to happen.
I'm so sorry.
I suppose I was naive to think
that I could make it
all the way through this game
without compromising my word,
but here we are.
I really wish I could
have saved you this time.
No hard feelings, guys.
All the best.
This isn't your friend wins.
Avi, wins immunity.
This is, who's played
the best game.
Avi, finally,
you have won probably
the most important
individual immunity challenge.
I don't think I've stepped out
of the game once.
I'm proud of who I've been
in this game.
I definitely think
that I deserve
to be the winner
of this competition.
Avi, I was there, from day one
you were always a huge threat.
You were supposed to go
after Sala.
How did you manage
to hang in there?
Um, well I think
Nate actually said
it pretty well, you know.
After had our conversation
he said,
"I don't want anyone to ever
look at me like that again".
Um, and you know, I...
I think it was just making sure
I didn't
just kind of, um, give up.
After Sala left, my whole
game kind of shattered
and broke because
Sala was my, you know,
my best friend
and comrade out there.
So, I had to really
reassess and, um, yeah,
just kind of listening
and being involved and, um,
yeah, trying to stay alive
for one day more.
A lot of people were surprised
you didn't take out Tom earlier.
Why didn't you?
- Um...
- I mean, look at him.
- I see him.
- He's beautiful!
He's got a gorgeous tan.
I'm pissed.
No um, Tom...
I said on the very first day
he was my biggest competition
in this game.
Um, and I wanted to be up
against my finest competition
at the end, um, to feel as
though I really deserved it.
Um, and Tom was such
an incredible player.
Um, you know, he's extremely
likeable and strong and, um,
you know, a physical
threat and I thought,
"If I'm going to win
this game then I should win
"against the person
I think should win".
Outstanding.
Shay, your mate Avi's... R-V.
R-V or Avi?
We'll do a tutorial after this.
- Avi.
Your mate Avi's game
was based on loyalty yet Tom,
your nemesis ended up
with that loyalty.
Were you,
are you gutted by that?
Uh, no, I'm not, I'm really not.
It's funny when I hear him
talking about,
um, how he saw Tom
as the biggest threat
and he was the best player...
I saw it the exactly same way
but that was the exact reason
why I was trying to get rid
of him and he's like,
"I want to keep him!"
I was like "But I want
to get rid of him"
and so I obviously lost
to the tan and the abs
and so I just decided
to take a seat in the jury.
Tony, Avi's game
was based on trust
but isn't Survivor
all about gaining trust
and then betraying that trust
at the right time?
It is, Matt.
It's a very situational thing
and the only people
who will truly understand it
are the ones
that were there
at the Survivor Arena.
AKA, you can be best mates
today and a week down
the track, you know,
you could be gunning
for each other.
It's Survivor, you know?
It's a bitter pill
to swallow when someone
does turn on you but I think
most of us have felt it
and, um, yeah...
No, full credit to Avi.
On ya Tony and thanks Avi.
Okay, Avi won the title
of Sole Survivor
but after the break
we have another winner...
The GEM People's Choice Award.
You don't want to miss it!
You're back live
with Survivor New Zealand.
We've heard how tough
this game is
but there were many
light moments you didn't see
and some of players found ways
to make the most
of their time on the island.
How does it feel to be
New Zealand's
first Survivor MILF?
Does that give
you a good feeling?
Oh, my God.
Heaven.
Really, we should be lying
on the mat eating this like,
um, a chocolate orgy.
Chocolate, I said.
Don't ever say that again.
Right, you're not sleeping
beside me tonight, Sala.
That's for sure.
I feel like that would
just be really weird
on New Zealand Survivor,
like if someone
was walking around naked
all the time.
Loads of people
love nudity in New Zealand.
Yeah.
Maybe this is my wakeup call.
Maybe I need to be
a male stripper now.
I've never felt
so great in my life.
Yeah it is what it is, eh, mate?
Classic Jak,
uh, that clip almost dedicated
to you and I know
that you're a banking officer
and the question
I had for you...
The one burning question
is do you think
you're in the right job?
Um, well the fact
that I couldn't stack a bloody
pile of coins', um, is...
Is pretty indicative of the fact
that I should not be working
in a bank.
Yeah, I'm not a banker.
- You're not a banker?
- No.
What are you going to do, mate?
Um, man, I haven't even
asked myself that.
Man, I should have come prepared
for that one um, nah...
What are you going to do
with your life?
I don't know man.
Um, nah, um, I don't know.
I've just been...
Since the show finished,
I've spent heaps of time
just looking after myself
and evaluating
where I was in life and, um,
I just put more energy
into myself
and focused on my putting
my energy into stuff
that was worth my energy,
you know what I mean?
Um...
- That's enough Jak.
- Sorry!
That's enough,
that's great, that's great.
We'll leave it there.
Um, so that was a bit of a look
at what you guys
did to pass the time by.
Hannah, I know that you were
at Redemption
for a little while by yourself,
what did you do there?
Um, a lot.
I like, came up
with this awesome like,
rice and bean rap, um,
yeah, man.
Do you want to hit us
with a bit of that now?
No, I'm good.
I did a lot of soul
searching and like,
re-eval... Like, just what
I wanted to do in my life.
Yeah, there was a lot of just...
It's so lonely
on Redemption Island.
It's so boring.
In terms of what you want
to do with your life,
I'm 40 and I'm still trying
to figure it out
so we've got plenty of time.
Okay, Survivor
is essentially a social game,
so we wanted to know
which player
made the biggest
connection with you at home.
And you've been voting
all season to decide
the Survivor New Zealand
People's Choice Award.
That player will receive
a seven-night luxury
travel package for two
to Tahiti,
valued at $8,000.
Plus a thousand bucks
thanks to GEM.
Okay, here we go.
Decided by you New Zealand,
the winner is...
Sala.
Not only were
you the winner Sala,
but I think
it was overwhelming, mate.
I know you were gutted
by your blindside
but New Zealand has spoken.
How good is this?
Yeah, oh, yeah, pretty
humbled, pretty humbled.
But, I need to make sure
I articulate how respectful
the move was in the first place
and so... Thanks Barb
that was pretty awesome.
I just want to make sure
that everyone knows
that you know Barb
was actually...
She played the biggest move
and that needs
to be respected
and articulated right now.
And so she, uh...
Loves flamingos you know...
Yeah, flamingos!
Yes!
The day she loves flamingos
she put her foot down
and, uh, played the biggest
blind side
in New Zealand Survivor, so...
The flamingo thing
has gone over my head but,
um, how sweet
has this ride been for you
just very quickly?
Ah, it's been full on brother.
Uh, people don't understand
how full on the whole context
of Survivor is and, uh...
And we've got a lot of support
from Whanau and friends
but I think
at the end of the day
we still need each other
because there's still a lot
of processing
and there's still a lot...
The only ones
that will understand
what we went through is us
and so, yeah...
I really appreciate
the opportunity.
Okay.
Sala, you've been great.
You all have.
But it's time to pull the pin
on our first season
of Survivor New Zealand.
Thank you for watching everyone.
Thank you for your support.
It's been an amazing ride.
Good night.